

Bernardo Di Chiara

Data Analyst

dichiarabernardo@gmail.com

Passionate about Statistics and Data Analysis. Strong logical and analytical skills, 20 years' experience in dealing with customer requirements. Critical thinker with attention to details. Excellent documentation skills.

Professional Skills

- Data Analysis Techniques (Data Cleansing, Data Preparation, Data Visualization), Machine Learning
- Statistics (Exploratory Data Analysis, Inferential Data Analysis, Regression Models)
- Databases: SQL, Hadoop, MapReduce, Spark
- Requirement Management
- Product/Feature/System Specifications
- Acceptance Test Cases Definition
- Best Practices' Development
- Agile approach
- Leading Functional Teams
- Coaching People
- Product Management
- Handling Customer Cases
- Consulting

Personal Skills

- Self-steering
- Critical Thinking
- Precise
- Passion-driven
- Balanced

Professional Achievements

- Being used several times as a model when developing internal practices related to requirement analysis
- Being acknowledged several times by colleagues for having added quality to internal and external product documentation
- Having received very good feedback (5,6/6) from the attendants to competence transfer sessions
- Having affected the decision of major customers to buy our solution
- Being ranked as Exceptional in the Yearly Performance Evaluation several times
- Receiving Achievement Award from the Product Line for the outstanding job

Language Skills

- Italian (native language)
- English (fluently)
- Finnish (good knowledge)

Computer Skills

- Operating Systems: Windows 10 and previous versions, Android
- Applications: common Office Applications (Word, PowerPoint, Excel, Outlook, browsers), Data Analysis SW (RStudio, Jupyter Notebook, Power BI, KNIME, RapidMiner), CADs (MS Visio), concurrent SW project tools (GitHub, Wiki, A360)
- Programming languages: R, Python (including Pandas library), SQL, HTML, (CSS, JavaScript, C++)

References



"Bernardo is a hardworking and task-oriented self-starter. He has a track record of delivering results

in time and with high quality" Antti Pikkusaari, Strategy Consultant & CEO at Aedon Oy



"He's a great team player" Timo Leppäkorpi, Manager



"It was a pleasure to work with Bernardo as he took full

responsibility to deliver high quality results all done through a keen focus on the customer and an ability to engage other team members in achieving results." Kevin Rowland, Business Development Manager, Nokia



"A combination of customer understanding, technical expertise and co-operation skills makes
Bernardo very valuable and pleasant

to work with" Tuija Hurtta, Product Manager at Nokia



"He is able to understand and analyze wide and complex topics" Seppo Huotari, Manager at Nokia CV: Bernardo Di Chiara Page 2

Work History

Current Activities

Studying to Improve my Data Analytics Skills

- Data Cleansing, Data Preparation, Data Visualization
- Programming in R and Python, Supervised and Unsupervised Machine Learning
- Statistics: Exploratory & Inferential Data Analysis, Regression Models
- Databases: SQL, Hadoop, MapReduce, Spark
- Tools: RStudio, Jupyter Notebook, Spyder, Power BI, GitHub, KNIME, RapidMiner
- User Experience Research Methods

Jan 2010 - Dec 2016

Senior System Architect

Nokia

- Leading functional teams and being responsible of creating and maintaining several feasibility studies and requirement specifications by using Agile approach
- Defining acceptance test scenarios together with test engineers
- Maintaining Statements of Compliance for several features and interfaces
- Supervising Master Thesis works (coaching)

May 2009 - Dec 2009

Sabbatical

Used for self-development (sailing, studying psychology)

Apr 2007 - Apr 2009

Product Planning Manager

Nokia Siemens Networks

- Defining the content of a new product by coordinating the work of a group of people and by actively participating in the specification
- Defining best practices and customizing a new requirement handling tool
- Facilitating the maintenance of the Road Map of different products
- Handling customer cases

Mar 2004 - Mar 2007

Senior Solution Manager

Nokia Networks

- Providing consulting work and designing customized solutions with major global customers by specifying new features and integrating with third party products
- Running internal competence transfer sessions to Marketing and to Engineers
- Creating and maintaining communication material

Mar 2003 - Feb 2004

Network Architect

Nokia Networks

 Being responsible for the specification of key functionality in system releases composed of several products (defining and documenting the requirements)

May 2001- Feb 2003

System Product Manager

Nokia Networks

- Collecting requirements from customers and giving input to Development regarding several end-to-end functionalities
- Creating and maintaining contacts with other Business Units in order to coordinate release contents and schedules and in order to support marketing activities

Apr 2000 - Apr 2001

Product Manager

Nokia Networks

- Collecting requirements from customers and giving input to Development
- Creating communication slide sets for internal and external purposes
- Contributing to the creation of marketing material (including Road Maps, Product Descriptions and Feature Descriptions)

Nov 1997 - Mar 2000

Senior System Engineer

Nokia Networks

- Being responsible of several front end and back end requirement specification projects (requirement specifications, feasibility studies, implementation specific.)
- Participating in Standardization as a Nokia Main Delegate in 3GPP forum

CV: Bernardo Di Chiara Page 3

Education

- Master of Science in Electric Engineering (110/110 with honor), Palermo's University, Italy
- General Certificate of Education from High School specializing in scientific studies, School Don Bosco Villa Ranchibile, Palermo, Italy

Courses

- Data Analytics (about 800 hours of study)
 - o Data Science Math Skills (grade: 97,9%) (by Duke University on Coursera, Sep 14th 2017)
 - Introduction to Probability and Data (grade: 98,7%) (by Duke University on Coursera, Oct 17th 2017)
 - o Inferential Statistics (grade: 100%) (by Duke University on Coursera, *Nov 28th 2017*)
 - o Linear Regression and Modeling (grade: 100%) (by Duke University on Coursera, *Mar* 14th 2018)
 - o The Data Scientist's Toolbox (grade: 100%) (by Johns Hopkins University on Coursera, *Dec 9th 2017*)
 - o R Programming (grade: 100%) (by Johns Hopkins University on Coursera, *Jan 16th 2018*)
 - Getting and Cleaning Data (grade: 100%) (by Johns Hopkins University on Coursera, Feb 19th 2018)
 - o Practical Machine Learning (grade: 100%) (by Johns Hopkins University on Coursera, *Apr 13th 2018*)
 - o Getting Started with Python (grade: 100%) (by University of Michigan on Coursera, Sep 5th 2018)
 - o Python Data Structures (grade: 100%) (by University of Michigan on Coursera, Sep 11th 2018)
 - Introduction to Data Science in Python (by University of Michigan on Coursera, Oct 9th 2018)
 - o SQL for Data Science (grade: 100%) (by University of California Davis on Coursera, May 19th 2018)
 - o Coursera Mentor Community, for the SQL course (grade: 100%) (by Coursera, Aug 13th 2018)
 - o Hadoop Platform and Application Framework (100) (University of California, San Diego, *Jun 29th 2018*)
 - Big Data (by TalentGate/Haaga-Helia University of Applied Sciences, May 23rd 2018)
- Self-Management, Leadership and Selling
 - Boosting Your Leadership Skills (grade: A-) (by Aalto University, Oct 8th 2016)
 - o Entrepreneurship training (by Nestholma, Jun 21st 2016)
 - Focused Mind (Web based course, 2012)
 - Creative Thinking (Web based course, 2003)
 - Presentation Skills (by Delta Training)
 - Cross Cultural Awareness (by Richard Lewis Communications)
 - Funnel Effective Sales Negotiation (by Jorma Kylander Oy)
- Training Path towards **Sailing** Instructor Qualification with the Royal Yachting Association (2007 2013)
- Quite few technical courses in the telecom / datacom field (1997 2016)

Other Interests

- Sailing
 - Forming and managing crews as a skipper is an excellent way to maintain team building and leadership skills. Running the boat allows nurturing goal setting and planning skills
- Boat maintenance and reparation work
 - An efficient way to improve problem solving capabilities
- Psychology (a lot of self-reading, including Freud, Goleman, Atkinson & Hilgard's, ...)
 - o Increases self-awareness and improves communication skills
- Playing keyboards and ukulele
 - o An excellent exercise for both the hemispheres of the brain
- Swimming
 - Healthy mind in a healthy body
- Trekking, Gardening
 - Enjoying nature and spending time outside

Where to Find More

in http://fi.linkedin.com/in/bernardodichiara

GitHub https://github.com/BerniHacker/CV/blob/master/README.md